Hello and welcome.
In this tutorial we'll be showing you how
to quickly and easily start mining Monero.
To do this we'll be downloading and installing
the official Monero wallet GUI.
This software is built by the community and
distributed by the Monero core team.
It has a convenient interface which will allow
you to start mining via P2Pool,
the most effective and simple way to start
earning Monero with your home PC!
Before getting started there are a couple
of prerequisites: Firstly, as a Windows user
you will need to have Kleopatra installed
while Linux and Mac users should have gpg
installed.
This software is used to verify the contents
of the files and folders we'll be downloading.
**Mac users beware, this tutorial doesn't
contain specific advice for you.
However, you should be able to follow the
linux instructions without too much trouble.**
In addition to this software you'll need 50GB
or more disk space free.
This is necessary for downloading either a
full of pruned copy of the blockchain.
This guide assumes no previous mining experience.
If you already have xmrig and/or the latest
version of the Monero daemon, you may wish
to to look at the official P2Pool repo
for more specific instructions.
We're going to start by visiting getmonero.org,
the official website of the Monero Core Team.
Feel free to browse the site and learn more
about Monero before continuing.
When you're ready, go ahead and click on the
Downloads tab.
The software we're interested in is the "Monero
GUI Wallet".
To download it, scroll down until you reach
the "Downloads" subheading.
Next, click and download the software which
matches both your hardware and operating system.
As I'm using Ubuntu, I'll be choosing the
64bit Linux version.
To check that these are the files intended
for use by the creators we’ll need two important
pieces of information:
Either a signed copy of the file hashes;
or a signature file ending with '.asc'
and the public key of the person who signed
them
We can find these files using the "Show hashes
to verify your download" drop-down menu.
The first link gives us a copy of the signed
hashes.
Simply right click and *save link as* to download
this text file.
To locate binaryfate's public key, we should
head back to the getmonero site and click
on the link entitled *in the source code*.
This link has taken us directly to binaryfate's
public key.
To download a copy, simply right click on
the *Raw* button and click *save link as*.
For the rest of the process please take a
look at our guide entitled Importing Public Keys & Verifying Hashes
Feel free to stop after watching the section
entitled **VERIFYING SIGNATURES & HASHES**,
as you can then return to this guide.
Make sure to use the files you have downloaded
now rather than the ones from the other video.
The process is exactly the same otherwise.
The following two sections cover installation
for Linux and windows separately.
Feel free to use the time stamps to get to
the section that suits you best.
By now you should have downloaded and verified
the contents of your download.
Now that's done, we're going to start by extracting
the contents of this zipped folder.
To do this, we need to simply right click
and select *Extract Here*.
Feel free to place this folder somewhere memorable,
or alongside your other program files.
Let's take a look through the folders.
We're looking for the file labelled *monero-wallet-gui.AppImage*.
Once found, we can start the program by double
clicking.
We'll first be asked if we want to create
a desktop entry, I'm going to select yes.
This will provide me with a handy icon to
select each time I want to start mining.
After that, we are ready to go.
To continue, please skip over the next section
which is meant for Windows users only.
By now you should have downloaded and verified
the contents of your download.
To install the software, simply extract the
contents of the zip file and then double click
on the installer.
We'll be prompted to navigate through a welcome
screen and then a licence agreement.
The Monero Wallet GUI is free and open source
software, so this agreement is shorter than
you may think.
After clicking accept and next we will now
need to choose where to install the software.
I'm going to choose the default location.
Next, we need to choose the location for our
blockchain data.
Don't worry about this 90GB requirement, this
has changed and will be covered again in the
next section.
Once again we'll select next.
I want the Monero software to appear in my
start menu, so I'll be leaving this section
as it is and moving on.
I don't want a desktop icon...
I just want to install the software :)
And there we have it.
Just a couple of things to do before we continue.
Let's start by opening the software from the
start menu.
We are now prompted to set some firewall rules.
I am going to deselect public networking and
allow private networking.
In the future, this will allow other computers
in my network to use the blockchain data hosted
on this computer.
With that done, it's time to add a rule to
Windows defender.
Windows may flag the Monero software as a
virus in the upcoming steps, so we'll need
to create an exclusion rule for the install
folder.
To do this we'll need to go to the virus and
threat protection settings.
You can find this by typing it in the search
bar or opening the start menu and typing in
**virus**.
Next, under Virus and Threat Protection Settings,
click on Manage Settings.
Scroll down until you see the *Exclusions*
section and select *Add or remove exclusions*.
Click *Add an exclusion*, choose folder and
then navigate to the folder that the Monero
Wallet GUI was installed to.
Finally, we're ready to continue.
Welcome to the Monero wallet GUI.
Feel free to set the language of the interface
before continuing.
Next we're going to select *Advanced mode*.
We're going to want to create a brand new
wallet.
This is because the primary address of your
miner will be visible to the P2Pool network.
It is good to think of this as a wallet dedicated
to mining only.
We're then prompted to choose a name for a
wallet, and a save location.
I'm going to be saving my wallet to an encrypted
drive, which I set up earlier.
We're also given an opportunity to record
our new seed phrase and the restore height.
These are important pieces of information
and act as the keys to the wallet.
After making a copy of this information, select
next and then enter a new, strong password
to encrypt the wallet file.
We recommend using password generators usually
bundled with managers such as Bitwarden and
KeePassXC.
When you're ready to continue, hit next.
Mining using this GUI is only possible with
the availability of a local node.
Hosting a local node is both great for the
security of others and your own personal privacy.
To run your own local node you need to download
a copy of the blockchain.
The entire Monero blockchain is currently
around 130GB in size.
It's constantly increasing in size and is
something you should keep in mind.
For those who don't have this amount of memory
to spare, you can alternatively download a
pruned copy of the blockchain, this currently
takes around 50GB of space.
Depending on your own circumstances you will
want to select different options.
We're going to download a full copy of the
blockchain to the default location, so all
that's left to do is click next once again.
To finish up, all we need to do is review
our settings and select *Create wallet* and
then enter the password we chose in the previous
step.
In the bottom left-hand corner of the landing
page you'll notice that the current network
status is labelled *Synchronising*.
Be prepared to wait a significant amount of
time for this process to complete.
It can take anywhere from 12 hours to a week.
The time it takes to complete will depend
on your blockchain choices, your hardware
and your internet speed.
Writing the blockchain to an SSD will guarantee
the best performance.
Currently we’re only leeching the blockchain
from the P2P network and sharing is caring
after all, so we’ll want to enable seeding
as well.
To do this, we’re going to have to set special
rules in the firewall to allow incoming connections
for the Monero Peer Network (18080) and the
P2Pool Peer Network (37889) on both our computers
and routers.
For information on how to do this, you can
check out our node setup guide which is linked below
Once your node is synchronised (as you can
see mine is now) it will be time for you to
move on to the next section.
Alright, it's nearly time to get our mining
underway.
Firstly, as a Windows user, you'll want to
close the software and start it again with administrative privileges.
This can be done by right clicking on the
start menu or desktop icon.
The software is now synchronised with the
rest of the network and we've now only got
a few more settings to change.
We're now to going to select the settings
tab from the menu and then node.
For now we're going to stop the daemon with
the button provided.
Next we're going to add the following flags
to the box provided.
You can find a copy of them in the video description.
These options help to ensure reliability and
security.
Once you've entered those settings, you can
restart the daemon.
To access the mining menu, click on the advanced
tab.
Here we want to change mode to P2Pool and
confirm we're using the mini side chain, which
is recommended for all new users.
We're going to leave everything else as default
for now.
Let's click Start mining.
To continue, the Monero software will need
to install the additional P2Pool software.
It will automatically install it to the same
location and all we have to do is select yes.
It will take a short while to download and
when it's done, you'll receive a prompt.
It's finally time to start mining!
So let's go ahead and select Start mining
once more.
At first you will see your status change to
Connected + Mining and once everything is
up and running, the Monero software will then
display your hashrate.
Your hashrate, is the speed at which your
computer is securing the network,
the greater your hashrate, the greater your
rewards!
There are two big incentives for miners to
use the P2Pool.
First is the low payout threshold and 0% fees
and the other is the ability to sign up to
the xmrvsbeast raffle.
If it's your first time hearing about the
xmrvsbeast raffle, here's what you need to know.
The raffle exists to incentivise miners, especially
those with low powered machines to contribute
the security of the network.
You can sign up to the raffle via the xmrvsbeast
website.
Before heading over there, let's first copy
our new address to the clipboard.
Registration gives you access to two different
reward streams.
The first is a sequential boost.
You can take a look at the boost dashboard
via the link.
For more details about how it works, just
click on rules.
Let's head back to the main raffle basboard.
Once again, for more details, click on rules.
Now that we've seen how this all works, let's
register.
To register, you'll need to enter the primary
address of the new wallet you created.
The token field should be left blank for new
registrations.
As we're new to mining, we'll initially receive
an error message.
This is because we're yet to prove that we're
actively mining.
Only once we've started making contributions
to the network will we be able to register successfully.
Once you've registered successfully, make
a note of the token you are issued with, as
this will be required in the future!
With your address and token, you can then
check the history of your wins, using the
link on the main page.
If you have any troubles with these steps
please head over to the xmrvsbeast subreddit
and search for similar issues before posting.
You may be wondering how to know when you
can successfully sign up to the raffle.
You can easily check the progress of your
miner remotely by visiting mini.p2pool.observer.
Here you can use your Monero address to search
and find your individual progress.
Once again, as we're new to mining we'll get
an error.
Only once we've begun finding shares will
we see information about the miner and its progress.
Once we see a valid share, we can then sign
up for the raffle.
To find out how often you may produce shares,
head back to the main page and select the
average share time calculator, punch in your
hashrate and you'll receive an estimate.
Let's take a look at another miners progress
to see an example.
Here you can see statistics from the miner
including average effort, blocks found and share positions.
Here the shares move from right to left with
time .
Below this you'll see information about each
payout and the shares which enabled those
payouts at the bottom.
Well, there you have it!
Hopefully you're now up and running and earning
those sweet rewards.
As a parting note, please remember this pool
is only possible because of the hard work
of contributors.
The main repository for p2pool can be found
in the description below.
If you're interested to know more about it's
features and how it works, including how to
set things up on different OSs, this is the
place to come.
And at the bottom of this page you will find
a donation address.
The people who work on these things do it
mostly for love rather than money, so every
donation goes to keeping them motivated.
We sincerely hope this guide has helped you
on your way to participating in Monero ecosystem.
If you're interested in more in depth guides,
please check out the other videos in our channel.
And if you found this useful and want to send
us a tip, our address can be found on screen now.
Anyway, that's all from us this time around.
So, thanks for watching and goodbye for now!
~moneroguides